Samantha Ruiz Mays

(386) 490-6828 | sami.mays93@gmail.com

linkedin.com/in/samantha-mays | https://samimays.github.io/personal_website/ | https://github.com/samimays

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Business analyst that has worked in diverse industries. Builds dashboards using business intelligence tools to better understand KPIs and provide actionable insights to leadership, and owns multiple data sources that provides the source of truth for the company data.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Technical Skills: MS Excel, MS PowerPoint, MS Power BI, MS Power Apps **Software**: Qlik Sense, Salesforce Marketing Cloud, Sisense, Snowflake

Programming Languages: Java, R, C#, HTML, CSS

Database: SQL, MS Access

WORK EXPERIENCE

Aptihealth, Population Health

June 2022 – October 2022

Data Analyst Remote

Worked with member engagement to send marketing materials to increase member platform usage. Worked on data analytics team to build dashboards that identified insightful KPIs our stakeholders could track for growth.

- Collaborated cross-functionally with 3 teams by building email templates using HTML, building journey entry data using SQL, and building logic for the journeys using logic provided by the engagement team. Built 3 journeys, which increased member engagement by 15% overall.
- Automated company's operations report that tracks referrals, diagnostic interviews, and sessions with our members, and compares them to the financial plan. Increased productivity for the financial manager by reducing 3 hours of computation time, and increasing the accuracy of the report by 10%.
- Investigated therapeutic alliance metrics by analyzing company's post-sessions survey data and uncovering new insights. Identified a metric that could track to improve therapeutic alliance, created a goal to improve the score by 3%, and provided 2 actionable ways to improve the metric.

Blue Water Shipping, O&E Projects

December 2021 - May 2022

Business Analyst

Houston, TX

Built tools to assist team members on daily activities and create dashboards to help upper management understand our KPIs and make improvements.

- Collaborated with our China team to build a script in R that combines data from three data sets with over 2,000 data points, cleans text data with 95% accuracy, and outputs a data file used for weekly calls with a client. With this script, production of the output file was increased by 900%.
- Learned how to build a web scraper using R. Using this skill, a script has been built to input data and collect the outputs on a specific website to calculate CO2 emissions on transit routes, removing manual work and decreasing calculation time by 40%.
- Designed a Power BI dashboard that tracks bids that have been completed and quotes that have been won for client shipments. Programmed a script to automatically extract the data, clean and upload it, resulting in the 1st automated in the company to track this KPI, allowing management to understand company's conversion rates.

LivaNova, Competitive Intelligence and Data Analytics Business Analyst/Associate Marketing Analyst

June 2019 – November 2021

Houston, TX

Aid team members and other departments in making informed decisions about the business through data analysis and data visualization.

- Led a team of 3 that built an alternative forecast model using R studio to predict end-of-service implants, helping Sales calculate their units sold quarterly target, and aiding Commercial Operations set goals for reaching out to patients to receive new devices. As a result, we have increased accuracy of predicted implants to be within 6% of actuals, and increased forecast production by 200%.
- Taught myself programming syntax for Qlik sense, the company's data modeling tool. Since learning this, 5 dashboards have been built while working collaboratively with 3 different business units, resulting in automated reporting, which helped these units be 50% more effective with actionable insights.

• Utilized a third-party vendor's database using SQL to identify Community Neurologists that refer patients to Comprehensive Epilepsy Centers for specific procedures. Found over 3,500 Neurologists for the Commercial Operations team that were potential new prospects for prescribing our device.

EDUCATION

University of Florida, Hough Graduate School of Business

Master of Science in Information Systems and Operations Management (ISOM)

May 2019 Gainesville, FL

• Track: Information Technology

• GPA: 3.78/4.00, KPMG Merit Scholarship Recipient

University of Florida, College of Health and Human Performance

Bachelor of Science – Applied Physiology and Kinesiology, Exercise Physiology

May 2016

Gainesville, FL

• GPA: 3.72/4.00, Summa Cum Laude